Guide to the Abraham Lincoln Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Abraham Lincoln collection
1824-1865
GEN MSS 257
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.8
(4 boxes)
Correspondence and writings by and about Abraham Lincoln, and a gold pen used by Lincoln. 4 ALS from Lincoln to Benjamin F. James, William M. Dickson, and to an unidentified recipient. Writings by Lincoln include an autograph praecipe issued by Lincoln for writ in his first law case, "David Woolridge vs. Hawthorne", and a fragment of a speech on slavery. Also present is a letter by Edwin Booth to Colonel A. Badeau concerning Lincoln's assassination by his brother, John Wilkes Booth, two days earlier; two volumes containing letters and writings by and about members of Lincoln's cabinet, including Andrew Johnson, Edwin M. Stanton, a letter to W. P. Fessenden regarding the attack on Petersburg, and Gideon Welles' autographed manuscript recollections on the formation of Lincoln's cabinet. Accompanied by the gold pen used by Lincoln to sign the Emancipation Proclamation, with accompanying documentation.
Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 4 and broadside folder 28: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Abraham Lincoln, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Material has been organized into two series: I, Gift of A. Conger Goodyear and II, Additional Materials, materials acquired from various sources.
Petersburg Crater, Battle of, Va., 1864; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; Badeau, Adam, 1831-1895; Booth, Edwin, 1833-1893; Booth, John Wilkes, 1838-1865; Dickson, William M. (William Martin), 1827-1889; Fessenden, William Pitt, 1806-1869; James, Benjamin Franklin; Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Stanton, Edwin M. (Edwin McMasters), 1814-1869; United States. President (1861-1865: Lincoln) ( Emancipation Proclamation)
- Gift of A. Conger Goodyear, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of A. Conger Goodyear, 1953
  - Abraham Lincoln ALS to Benjamin F. James, Springfield, 1845 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Discusses the possibility of securing enough votes in the Illinois State Convention to nominate him as Whig Candidate for Congress
  - Autograph page from Lincoln's sum book, dealing with simple interest, [ca. 1824] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Bound in dark green morocco
  - Autograph praecipe issued by Lincoln for writ in his first law case, "David Woolridge vs. Hawthorne", 1836 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bound in three quarters green morocco
  - Fragment of a speech on slavery, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Refers to Senator Stephen Douglas. Bound in dark green morocco
  - 6 typescript and typescript carbon letters concerning the autograph praecipe and fragment of a speech on slavery, including a letter from Carl Sandburg, 1926 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ALS from Edwin Booth to Colonel A. Badeau concerning the assassination of Abraham Lincoln by his brother, John Wilkes Booth, two days earlier, [1865] Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Also bound in the volume are a manuscript transcription of the letter and a play bill of the performance at Ford's Theater the night of the assassination. Bound in three quarters dark green morocco
  - Three typescript carbon copies of the letter from Booth to Badeau, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Abraham Lincoln and his Cabinet, bound volume of letters and documents by and about members of his cabinet. Vol. 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Bound in dark green morocco. Items in volume are analyzed below in the order in which they appear
    - Lincoln, Abraham. Survey of a tract of land entirely in Lincoln's handwriting, 1836 Nov 16
    - Hay, John. ALS, n.d.
    - Hamlin, Hannibal. ALS to M. Titcomb, Bangor, [Maine], 1879 May 17
      Refers to eventful years of the Republic through which he has passed, etc.
    - Harrington, George. ALS to William P. Fessenden, Bern, Switzerland, 1868 Sept 26
    - Seward, William H. ALS to [Samuel] Blatchford, Washington, D.C., [1862] Dec 22
      Refers to a Cabinet crisis which is past, the Trent Affair, the stability of the country, and the loyalty of the people. Says that he has urged Weed to go to Europe. Asks his correspondent to send him some wine
    - Johnson, Andrew. ALS to William M. Lowry, Nashville, Tenn., 1856 Dec 14
      Confidential political letter, refers to possibility of his going to the Senate, etc.
    - Seward, William H. autograph ms. signed of his "Oration on the Probable Permanency of the Union" delivered at the Commencement at Union College in 1820 as Representative of the Adelphi Society
      Seward was at this time only nineteen years of age. He entered Union College in 1816, taught school for six months in 1819, and returned to college to graduate in 1820. This paper shows Seward's strong support of the permanency of the Union
    - Chase, Salmon P. ALS to Governor Nathaniel Prentice Banks, Springfield, Mass., 1860 [i.e. 61] Jan 7
      Chase refers to being in Springfield at Lincoln's request and his impressions on meeting Lincoln. The object of the meeting was to discuss Chase's possible inclusion in Lincoln's cabinet
    - Fessenden, William Pitt. ALS to his son Francis Fessenden, Portland [Maine], 1865 Jun 6
      Refers to Sherman's "behaving like a fool" and other matters of public interest
    - McCulloch, Hugh. ANS to Gideon Welles, [Washington, D.C.], 1866 Mar 15[?]
    - Stanton, Edwin McMasters. ALS to [Charles Anderson] Dana, Washington, 1862 Feb 2
      Refers to the military operations. Says that the War Department is "poisoned with treason or helpless from imbecility". Proposes to commence the reorganization.
    - Harrington, George. ALS to W. P. Fessenden, [Washington], 1864 Aug 1
      The letter concerns the attack on Petersburg and the blowing up of the "Crater"
    - Cameron, Simon. ALS to W. P. Fessenden, Washington, 1864 Sep 10
      Says "the campaign will be short and must be urged with vigor"
    - Smith, Caleb Blood. ALS to [Richard] Wallach, Connersville [Ind.], 1848 Oct 9
      Refers to the Free Soil Movement, General Taylor, etc.
    - Blair, Montgomery. ALS to Gideon Welles, Washington, 1874 Jan 22
      Speaks of Seward and contrasts his character with that of Lincoln. This letter shows plainly Blair's antagonism to Seward and relates to his intrigues in reation to Fort Sumter, etc.
    - Lee, J. ALS to Montgomery Blair, Washington, [1874] Jan 22
    - Bates, Edward. ALS to Gideon Welles, Washington, 1863 Jun 6
      With franked addressed envelope, gives his views on how to crush the Rebellion
    - Speed, James. ALS to Abraham Lincoln, Louisville, KY, 1862 Nov 10
      Regarding the appointment of a judge
    - Miscellaneous material found in volume 1, 1864-1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Two engraved portraits of Salmon P. Chase, pieces of bookseller's catalogue, and clippings: one carrying an article on "The President's Plan of Conciliation -- The Greased Cartridge Policy" from 1864, and another from 1928 about a Lincoln letter
  - Abraham Lincoln and his Cabinet, bound volume of letters and documents by and about members of his cabinet. Vol. 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Welles, Giddeon. Autograph ms, recollections in regard to the formation of Mr. Lincoln's Cabinet, n.d.
      Contains much information about the negotiations and discussions on appointments to the Cabinet following Lincoln's election
    - Speed, Joshua Fry. ALS to Gideon Welles, Louisville, Kentucky, 1872 Aug 8
      Denies statements made in Lamon's "Life of Lincoln" in reference to Lincoln's offering a cabinet position to Guthrie
    - Babcock, James Fairchild. 2 ALS to Gideon Welles, New Haven, Conn., 1868 Feb
      Refers to conversations with Lincoln on cabinet appointments
    - Davis, David. ALS to Gideon Welles, Bloomington, Ill., 1872 Jul 27
      Discusses Lincoln's Cabinet appointments and Speed's statement in regard to the reported offer to Guthrie
    - Swett, Leonard. ALS to Thurlow Weed, Bloomington, Ill., 1860 Dec 10
      On second sheet is an ALS from David Davis to Thurlow Weed, discussing Lincoln's invitation to visit him at Springfield and advises Weed to accept, accompanied by typescript copies of both letters
    - Yates, Richard. 2 LS to Schuyler Colfax, Springfield, Ill., 1861 Feb
      Tells of recommending Colfax to Lincoln for a cabinet appintment and of journey to Washington as a companion and secretary to Lincoln. Yates includes a copy of his letter to Lincoln recommending Colfax.
    - Miscellaneous material found in volume 2: typescripts of two letters (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Additional Materials, Series II
  Other materials received from various sources
  - Lincoln, Abraham. ALS to William M. Dickson, Springfield, Ill., 1859 Oct 17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Mounted on a leaf from an album, with related newspaper clippings Gift, 1955
  - Lincoln, Abraham. ALS to William M. Dickson, Springfield Ill., 1860 Jun 7 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Concerning a bill claimed by Johnson, Saunders & Co., Cincinnati Gift, 1955
  - Lincoln, Abraham. ANS to an unidentified recipient, [Washington], and five photographs of Lincoln (Box 2, Folder 14)
    ANS ordering a discharge from service Accompanied by a clipping describing his visit to New Haven Gift, 1955
  - Bishop, Albert Webb. ALS to Abraham Lincoln, Washington, D.C., 1865 Feb 13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Endorsed by Lincoln: "Will the Secretary of War and Gen. Halleck please consider the application?... Feb 15 1865"; also endorsed by Secretary Stanton, asks permission for a stock of goods to be transported to Arkansas
  - The gold pen used by Lincoln to sign the Emancipation Proclamation in the Executive Mansion, Washington, D.C., 1863 Jan 1
    Gift, 1965
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Oversize, box 3, folder 24
  - Documents Accompanying the Pen
    - Autographed photograph of Louis Burgdorf, Washington, D.C. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - ALS by Daniel N. Morgan, ex-U.S. Treasurer, Bridgeport Conn. To Mrs. W. B. Tucker, Lansing, Michigan., 1928 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Photocopy of signed and witnessed affirmation by Louis Burgdorf, Washington D.C., 1894 June 27
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
    - Photocopy of testification, signed by U.S. Treasury officials, Washington, D.C., 1894 June 28
    - LS by George S. Godard, State Librarian, Connecticut State Library, Hartford, Conn, to Mrs. W. B. Tucker, Lansing, Michigan, 1928 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Duplicate original affidavit (two pages) by Myra A. Tucker, at Lansing, Michigan; signed, witnessed and sworn to before Hiram J. De Vries, Notary Public, Ingham County, Michigan, 1928 Nov 28 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - History of the pen, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Photocopy of frontispiece, and pages 45-46, Anderson Galleries, New York, NY catalogue sale, 1929 Feb 27 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Photocopies of pages 73 and 74, Parke-Bernet Galleries, New York, NY catalogue sale, 1951 Nov 13 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Photocopies of pages 39-41, Parke-Bernet Galleries, New York, NY catalogue sale, 1958 Nov 5 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Oversize, n.d.
  - The gold pen used by Lincoln to sign the Emancipation Proclamation in the Executive Mansion, Washington, D.C., 1863 Jan 1 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photocopy of signed and witnessed affirmation by Louis Burgdorf, Washington D.C., 1894 June 27 (Box bsd, folder 25)
  - Photocopy of testification, signed by U.S. Treasury officials, Washington, D.C., 1894 June 28 (Box bsd, folder 26)
- Restricted Fragile Materials
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 5 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box bsd, folder 28)